<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[A tutorial a day]]></title>
  <link href="http://dpac56.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dpac56.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-07T09:57:43+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://dpac56.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Deepak]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 2: UX Crash Course]]></title>
    <link href="http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/ux-crash-course/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-07T09:21:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/ux-crash-course</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>A crash course on UX</h3>

<p><em>I am always bookmarking interesting tutorials that I would do one fine day. Since that day never comes, I have aimed to do one tutorial each day. The topics would broadly be programming, design, marketing and productivity tips. All credit to the original tutorials &ndash; I am just thinking aloud as I type my notes &amp; views on what I read.</em></p>

<p>Day 2: The UX Crash Course <a href="http://thehipperelement.com/post/75476711614/ux-crash-course-31-fundamentals">http://thehipperelement.com/post/75476711614/ux-crash-course-31-fundamentals</a></p>

<h3>What is UX</h3>

<p>A process to make users more effective in whatever their indivdiual goals are.</p>

<h3>Goals</h3>

<p>The core concept here is two pronged: First, find the user &amp; business goals and second, align those goals. It is fascinating that this crash course starts with this point, because I have been part of teams where websites/applications were developed in an environment of zero possibility of this happening. Designers/developers had minimum access to top management to understand the goals (well apart from knowing what the business does) and had no interaction with end users.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, in most practical cases there are plenty of restrictions (time, money, resources) that relegate UX to UI and UI to only following the current best practises.</p>

<p>Either way &ndash; there is no denying that designing experiences without understanding stakeholders is not the best way.</p>

<h3>Ingredients of UX</h3>

<p>Okay so this section is very nicely done &ndash; lots of questions that you should bookmark <a href="http://thehipperelement.com/post/72080847673/daily-ux-crash-course-3-of-31">http://thehipperelement.com/post/72080847673/daily-ux-crash-course-3-of-31</a> . Irrespective of whether you have a full team working or running a single person shop, I guess asking these questions at various stages of progress can only make things better.</p>

<p>The 5 ingredients listed are Pyschology (get into the mind of users, their goals &amp; motivations), Usability (visualize the actions of users, how they use your design), Design (estimate the impressions your design makes on users), Copywriting (Are you using generic text or everything is optimized) and Analysis (Measure, measure, measure)</p>

<p>Couple of points here &ndash; a good UX designer would be exceptionally good in getting into the mind of users. Obviously, there is only a degree to which this is possible. But, if you can track what made the user come to your site, what did he want and how did he go about searching for it &ndash; your designs would start aligning the goals.</p>

<p>The other interesting point is something that is quite new to me &ndash; the copywriting used by the UX designer. I suspect a vast majority of time is spent on visual design and text is treated as commoditized work.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 1: Creating an Octopress Blog on Github]]></title>
    <link href="http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/06/creating-a-github-blog-using-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-06T12:15:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/06/creating-a-github-blog-using-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Building an Octopress Blog on Github</h3>

<p><em>I am always bookmarking interesting tutorials that I would do one fine day. Since that day never comes, I have aimed to do one tutorial each day. The topics would broadly be programming, design, marketing and productivity tips. All credit to the original tutorials &ndash; I am just thinking aloud as I type my notes.</em></p>

<p>Day 1: Getting started with Octopress <a href="http://www.tomordonez.com/blog/2012/06/04/creating-a-github-blog-using-octopress/">http://www.tomordonez.com/blog/2012/06/04/creating-a-github-blog-using-octopress/</a></p>

<p>Octopress is a static blogging framework that calls itself “A blogging framework for hackers”. The tutorial at tutsplus (<a href="http://dev.tutsplus.com/tutorials/getting-started-with-octopress--webdesign-11442">http://dev.tutsplus.com/tutorials/getting-started-with-octopress&#8211;webdesign-11442</a>) does a good job of explaining what is the difference between such a static framework and something like Wordpress that needs to ‘do’ something on the server before becoming viewable.</p>

<p>Octopress in itself is pretty famous and used by a lot of programmers. I was a bit wary that the Octopress site hasn’t been updated for a few years and toyed with the idea of trying out Pelican &ndash; that does almost the same thing but is Python based. Maybe, will do that later.</p>

<p>You would need Ruby version 1.9.3 or above for this to work. And since my machine didn’t have that I had to use the Ruby Version Manager (rvm).</p>

<p>As soon as I put in the first command of the tutorial, out popped a message that rvm on Ubuntu is unusable. Good thing though that the link given pointed to a Stackoverflow answer that worked perfectly.</p>

<p>You had to remove the rvm completely and reinstall as per these instructions.</p>

<p>Follow the instructions, and finally when it all ends run the command ruby &mdash;version. It should output to the latest one. I now have 2.1.0</p>

<p>With Ruby you also need RubyGems &ndash; a package management framework for Ruby. Broadly, the programs/libraries/codes in Ruby are in a self contained format called a gem. With RubyGems you can install any of these open source packages directly from the command line.</p>

<p>The commands to install Octopress are pretty simple.</p>

<p>Go to a convenient folder and clone the main repo</p>

<pre><code>git clone git://github.com/imathis/octopress.git octopress
cd octopress
rake install
</code></pre>

<p>At this stage, you are actually ready to see your blog locally with the following</p>

<pre><code>rake preview
</code></pre>

<p>Go to localhost:4000 in your browser &amp; you should see the default theme</p>

<p><em>The deploying to github part is also straightforward but gave me a lot of headache.</em></p>

<p>This is what you need to do. Create a new github repository with name as username.github.com</p>

<p>Run</p>

<pre><code>rake setup_github_pages
</code></pre>

<p>You will need to enter the repository URL in the terminal when prompted. The suggested format is</p>

<pre><code>git@github.com:username/username.github.com.git
</code></pre>

<p>However, entering this format (&amp; after completing the process) I could not deploy on github and kept getting an invalid repository/check access rights error. Finally, I tried entering in this format</p>

<pre><code>git@github.com:username/username.github.com
</code></pre>

<p>And everything worked &ndash; so if you are having some troubles, try checking with the second option as well.</p>

<p>Pushing to github:</p>

<pre><code>rake generate
git add .
git commit -am "Message"
git push origin source
rake deploy
</code></pre>

<p>That should be it and your blog should be viewable on username.github.com (or .io) in some minutes.</p>

<p>Everytime you create a new post</p>

<pre><code>rake new_post ["My first post"]
</code></pre>

<p>they will be stored in the octopress/source/_posts folder and after each modification you can run the above set of git commands to see the changes.</p>

<p>A couple of points:</p>

<ol>
<li>If you are still having trouble, check that the default branch of your github repo is &lsquo;master&rsquo; and not &lsquo;source&rsquo;</li>
<li>The posts in Octopress are in Markdown format &ndash; it is pretty easy to learn &amp; is bare bones. This is where you can take a look <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax#list">http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax#list</a></li>
</ol>


<p>These links might also help in your specific problems:</p>

<p><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/12060903/github-error-repository-not-found-when-installing-octopress">http://stackoverflow.com/questions/12060903/github-error-repository-not-found-when-installing-octopress</a></p>

<p><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/11240797/git-commit-error-repository-invalid">http://stackoverflow.com/questions/11240797/git-commit-error-repository-invalid</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
