<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[A tutorial a day]]></title>
  <link href="http://dpac56.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dpac56.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-13T12:07:08+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://dpac56.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Deepak]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 7: Introduction to Flask]]></title>
    <link href="http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/12/introduction-to-flask/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-12T11:04:47+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/12/introduction-to-flask</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I am always bookmarking interesting tutorials that I would do one fine day. Since that day never comes, I have aimed to do one tutorial each day. The topics would broadly be programming, design, marketing and productivity tips. All credit to the original tutorials &ndash; I am just thinking aloud as I type my notes &amp; views on what I read.</em></p>

<p>Day 7: Introduction to Flask <a href="http://code.tutsplus.com/tutorials/an-introduction-to-pythons-flask-framework--net-28822">http://code.tutsplus.com/tutorials/an-introduction-to-pythons-flask-framework&#8211;net-28822</a></p>

<p>Flask is one of the more popular web frameworks in Python.</p>

<p>What is a web framework? A web framework is a software framework that helps in development of dynamic websites/applications by performing the common tasks associated in web development so that you do not have to write them again.</p>

<p>Flask is a micro-framework written in Python ideally designed for smaller applications.</p>

<p>***Installing virtualenv</p>

<p>Invariably, almost every Python tutorial will start by installing virtualenv. This is a very useful tool that creates an isloated environment for your project. Why? Because in all probability you would need various dependencies/libraries in various versions for each project. If you do a system wide installation of these libraries and something changes &ndash; every project will be affected which you don&rsquo;t want.</p>

<pre><code>virtualenv --version
</code></pre>

<p>If the above command does not return anything, then you have to install through</p>

<pre><code>sudo pip install virtualenv
</code></pre>

<p>or</p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install python-virtualenv
</code></pre>

<h3>Installing Flask</h3>

<p>I have seen various ways of using virtualenv, but these seems the most convenient. Use virtualenv to make the main project folder</p>

<pre><code>virtualenv flaskapp
</code></pre>

<p>Now you have a folder which can be used as an isolated environment. Don&rsquo;t forget to activate virtualenv</p>

<pre><code>cd flaskapp
. bin/activate
</code></pre>

<p>Install Flask</p>

<pre><code>pip install Flask
</code></pre>

<h3>Project directory structure</h3>

<p>This tutorial actually did a much better job of easing into showing a directory structure.</p>

<p>Inside flaskapp/ make a folder app/ that will create all your files.</p>

<p>app/static/ will have your css, js, img
app/static/templates/ will have the web templates
app/routes.py will be the main python file that will contain the logic
app/README.md will be the normal description file.</p>

<h3>Using templates</h3>

<p>You don&rsquo;t want to repeat the HTML boilerplate code everytime so web templates come in handy in defining a parent template and then other inheriting most things from that + adding something of their own.</p>

<p>In your app/templates/ folder create a layout.html file with the below code.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;Flask App&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;

    &lt;body&gt;

        &lt;header&gt;
            &lt;div class="container"&gt;
                &lt;h1 class="logo"&gt;Flask App&lt;/h1&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/header&gt;

        &lt;div class="container"&gt;
            {block content}
            {endblock}

        &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/body&gt;

&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre>

<blockquote><p>Having troubles with Jekyll tags so code samples here will be without the &lsquo;%&rsquo; sign &ndash; ADD THEM IN THE PROGRAMS</p></blockquote>

<p>Either way this is a base layout that has a block tag in the second container class.</p>

<pre><code>{extends "layout.html"}
{block content}
&lt;div class = "jumbo"&gt;
    &lt;h2&gt; Welcome to the Flask app &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt; This is the home page for Flask app &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
{endblock}
</code></pre>

<p>If we create a home.html file as above &ndash; that can simply extend the layout. html file and insert its own code block in between.</p>

<p>So now the templates can be rendered. In a simple app like this the application logic only extends to routing to the correct page. The below is a standard Flask template in routes.py.</p>

<pre><code>from flask import Flask, render_template

app = Flask(__name__)      

@app.route('/')
def home():
 return render_template('home.html')

if __name__ == '__main__':
 app.run(debug=True)
</code></pre>

<p> We imported two functions Flask and render_template</p>

<p> Created a new instance of the Flask class</p>

<p> Defined what the program should do if the request is for the &lsquo;/&rsquo; page.</p>

<p> Okay, now cd into the app folder (make sure the virtualenv is activated) and run routes.py</p>

<p> You should be able to see a working web page on local host.</p>

<p> You could now add some styling to the page by adding a main.css file in the static folder. The only think to note here is how you add the link to the layout.html file head</p>

<pre><code>&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href=""&gt;;
</code></pre>

<p>Creating another page (about.html) follows the same process. Add a template in the templates folder and add the correct routing to the routes.py file</p>

<p>Okay so the only thing left here is to add some navigation to the home page. We will add the following to the layout.html file header</p>

<pre><code>&lt;strong&gt;&lt;nav&gt;
    &lt;ul class="menu"&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href = ""&gt;Home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href = ""&gt;About&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Well that is about that. We have a siimple working Flask website here that routes and introduces templates.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 6: UX Crash Course Contd..]]></title>
    <link href="http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/11/day-6-ux-crash-course-contd-dot/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-11T07:10:15+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/11/day-6-ux-crash-course-contd-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I am always bookmarking interesting tutorials that I would do one fine day. Since that day never comes, I have aimed to do one tutorial each day. The topics would broadly be programming, design, marketing and productivity tips. All credit to the original tutorials &ndash; I am just thinking aloud as I type my notes &amp; views on what I read.</em></p>

<p>Day 6: The UX Crash Course <a href="http://thehipperelement.com/post/75476711614/ux-crash-course-31-fundamentals">http://thehipperelement.com/post/75476711614/ux-crash-course-31-fundamentals</a></p>

<h3>Scanning patterns: Users don&rsquo;t read, they scan</h3>

<p>Readers scan &ndash; they stop at something that catches their eye, or keep moving on.</p>

<p>The F pattern: Normally, the scanning would be expected to happen in a &lsquo;F&rsquo; or &lsquo;E&rsquo; pattern. That is people will start on the top left &ndash; read right. Then restart on left, skip down a bit, read right if something interesting catches eye. Restart on left &amp; keep moving down. What does this mean? This means that a button on top left will have more chance of being seen than on the top right. That people follow patterns &amp; that you need to be aware of them (or test by heat maps).</p>

<h3>Browsing Vs Searching Vs Discovery</h3>

<p>You must find out which of the above define why users come to your site &ndash; for each would require a different design.</p>

<p>Browsing = Just looking around a store. Users might have shopped here before or heard good things from others. Eitherway they are in a quick scanning mode. Don&rsquo;t overcrowd things &ndash; make them quick &amp; visual.</p>

<p>Searching = specfically looking for something. They will want to systematically go through the options. Filters are good. At first glance users should see the critcial info that motivates them to click further. How much of the info is critical will be a careful choice to not make the design cluttered.</p>

<p>Discovery = Find something that you were not really looking for but allied to why you came to the store for. For the designer this is the question of how to lead people to something they don&rsquo;t know about but would find useful (according to you). Banners don&rsquo;t work &ndash; neither do putting more things in the menu. Think more on the lines of &ndash; If you liked this, you might also like this.</p>

<h3>Page Framework</h3>

<p>Footers &amp; navigation needs to be consistent across all pages.</p>

<p>Main menu is probably the most important thing on your site. Arrange the most important items left to right or top to bottom. Huge sub-menus are never a great idea (unless you positively have not other way)</p>

<p>Be consistent across all pages.</p>

<h3>The Fold, Images &amp; Headlines</h3>

<p>The Fold &ndash; part of your design that is visible before the user scrolls</p>

<p>A large % of users might scroll down, but you must make it clear why they should do that.</p>

<p>Images of people = good. The more emotion an image adds, the better.</p>

<p>Understand that not only the Headline itself is important, but it will also attract attentions to the parts around it. So, if the parts around a headline are not important you are only diverting user attention.</p>

<h3>The Axis of Interaction</h3>

<p>The users will focus attention on edges of alignment you have created. So if you want something to be clicked place it along those edges.</p>

<h3>Forms</h3>

<p>Keep them simple &amp; short.</p>

<p>The information you need will define the questions. The questions will define the input type you use.</p>

<p>Instructions &amp; labels: Don&rsquo;t assume things. Make it clear what you want.</p>

<p>Avoid mistakes in form filling by a) Giving an example answer/format and b) Allowing for common format variations. If there are mistakes make sure the user is guided to the exact field that needs to be corrected.</p>

<h3>Calls to action, Instructions and Labels</h3>

<p>Calls to action: Verb + Benefit + Urgency</p>

<p>Instructions &amp; labels: No lingo. No industry terms. Simple &amp; Clear</p>

<p>Button Labels: Don&rsquo;t give confusing labels like Ok or Yes. Give direct words: Save / Delete etc</p>

<h3>Primary &amp; Secondary Buttons</h3>

<p>Primary Buttons: Lead to actions that are productive for your business like buying, registering etc. These need to be with higher contrast and on the axis.</p>

<p>Secondary Buttons: Lead to actions that you need to provide but don&rsquo;t want used much like cancelling/deleting profile etc. Lighter contrast &amp; Off Axis.</p>

<p>Special Buttons: Unique (&amp; likely the most important) for your app. Give them a special (pattern breaking) treatment.</p>

<h3>User Psychology &ndash; Conditioning</h3>

<p>People do things where they are rewarded and shy away from punishements. These are not actual tangibles but perceptions. Can you create a loop where people are motivated to do some action and the feedback on that action created motivation for next action?</p>

<p>Conditioning comes into play when since people received a positive feeling 9 out of 10 times, they will come again to do the same.</p>

<h3>User Psychology &ndash; Persuasion</h3>

<p>This was a great topic &amp; if you are into core UX design I have a feeling that the author&rsquo;s book would be a great resources.</p>

<p>These are the 8 attributes of persuasion:</p>

<ol>
<li>Credibility: Have you shown why they should trust you</li>
<li>Know your audience: If you don&rsquo;t know your audience, how will you know what they look for?</li>
<li>Open &amp; Disarm: Open with the user&rsquo;s interest immediately. You need to get them engaged with a headline or a great photo</li>
<li>Create Rapport: Make them feel a part of the group by using words they understand</li>
<li>Isolate: When you have sufficiently advanced them on a path, focus on one thing</li>
<li>Convince: You might need another wave of info to convince them</li>
<li>Close the deal: A simple click to finish the transaction</li>
<li>Continue: Follow up even after the deal</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 5: UX Crash Course Contd..]]></title>
    <link href="http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/10/day-5-ux-crash-course-contd-dot/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-10T16:39:23+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/10/day-5-ux-crash-course-contd-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I am always bookmarking interesting tutorials that I would do one fine day. Since that day never comes, I have aimed to do one tutorial each day. The topics would broadly be programming, design, marketing and productivity tips. All credit to the original tutorials &ndash; I am just thinking aloud as I type my notes &amp; views on what I read.</em></p>

<p>Day 5: The UX Crash Course <a href="http://thehipperelement.com/post/75476711614/ux-crash-course-31-fundamentals">http://thehipperelement.com/post/75476711614/ux-crash-course-31-fundamentals</a></p>

<h3>Visual weight, contrast &amp; depth</h3>

<p>The premise is that we should aid users in noticing &amp; discovering the important parts and restrain them from being distracted by the not so important ones.</p>

<p>The more important things should have higher contrast: If the background is light they should be the darkest (&amp; vice-versa). They should also be bigger.</p>

<h3>Color</h3>

<p>This may be infringing on a UI designer&rsquo;s task but sometimes colors have intuitive meaning that serve some UX function. You might want to experiment with colors &ndash; though if that is not within your skills, leave that for the UI people.</p>

<h3>Repetition &amp; Pattern Breaking</h3>

<p>Focus is shifted towards where a pattern is broken. The brain treats a repetition as a single set but automatically treats a change as a new element.</p>

<h3>Line tension &amp; Egde tension</h3>

<p>A bit tricky one this &ndash; didn&rsquo;t fully get the concept.</p>

<h3>Alignment &amp; Proximity</h3>

<p>A basic but powerful concept. The closer objects are, the more likely they will be treated as belonging together. Alignment can create seperate groups in our mind as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 4: UX Crash Course Contd..]]></title>
    <link href="http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/09/day-4-optimizing-productivity/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-09T08:14:42+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/09/day-4-optimizing-productivity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I am always bookmarking interesting tutorials that I would do one fine day. Since that day never comes, I have aimed to do one tutorial each day. The topics would broadly be programming, design, marketing and productivity tips. All credit to the original tutorials &ndash; I am just thinking aloud as I type my notes &amp; views on what I read.</em></p>

<p>Day 4: The UX Crash Course <a href="http://thehipperelement.com/post/75476711614/ux-crash-course-31-fundamentals">http://thehipperelement.com/post/75476711614/ux-crash-course-31-fundamentals</a></p>

<h3>Information Architecture</h3>

<p>Information architecture is structuring how your content would be presented. In a simplistic way it is a Site Map.</p>

<p>Site Map shows various pages according to the levels in which they are presented and underlines the navigation possibilities.</p>

<p>There can broadly be two type of site maps: Flat &ndash; more categories in the top menu but each sub-menu is relatively less populated. Deep &ndash; less categories in the top menue but each sub-menu goes down to more levels.</p>

<h3>User stories</h3>

<p>A user story is a possible path that a user would take while going through your website. There might be a number of such stories for different users &amp; these stories in conjunction with Information architecture are important to maintain a clear communication with the design team and others.</p>

<p>There is a very important point here &ndash; don&rsquo;t write a user story &amp; give it to the UX designer, it is to be the other way round. The UX designer has to figure out the stories since they will have a major impact on the final design.</p>

<p>Getting back to Information architecture &ndash; this was a fascinating snippet. The architecture can be of various type from the most obvious/common top menu of Categories to Tasks (buy/sell), Time(Reddit), People(Facebook) etc</p>

<h3>Wireframes</h3>

<p>Wireframe isn&rsquo;t a sketch or a mind map or a discussion point. It is the final blueprint that will define your site. Plan &amp; build it carefully.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 3: UX Crash Course Contd..]]></title>
    <link href="http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/08/day-2-ux-crash-course-contd-dot/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-08T09:12:29+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/08/day-2-ux-crash-course-contd-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I am always bookmarking interesting tutorials that I would do one fine day. Since that day never comes, I have aimed to do one tutorial each day. The topics would broadly be programming, design, marketing and productivity tips. All credit to the original tutorials &ndash; I am just thinking aloud as I type my notes &amp; views on what I read.</em></p>

<p>Day 3: The UX Crash Course <a href="http://thehipperelement.com/post/75476711614/ux-crash-course-31-fundamentals">http://thehipperelement.com/post/75476711614/ux-crash-course-31-fundamentals</a></p>

<h3>User Research</h3>

<p>Do it often, do it in various stages. Everyone agrees that user research is important, it is how to do it where people falter.</p>

<h4>Subjective Research:</h4>

<p>These are questions more based on opinion and impressions. &ldquo;Do you trust this brand, were you happy with the search process&rdquo;. There is no way to prove them to be right or wrong but the larger the sample size &ndash; the closer to the effective answer you would be. [The most effective answer may or may not be the correct one!]</p>

<h4>Objective Research:</h4>

<p>These are hard facts that you might have seen in something like Google Analytics &ndash; Traffic, time spent on a page, bounce rate etc. There is no disputing what you see here.</p>

<h3>How to ask questions</h3>

<p>To me, this is perhaps the most important part of UX design &amp; the tutorial is a bit thin here. For anyone interested Coursera&rsquo;s Human Computer Interaction course is phenomenal in teaching these concepts.</p>

<p>Broadly: Be wary that the questions you ask determine the answers you get. Leading questions that already assume something are a bad bad thing &ldquo;Which part of the process did you enjoy most&rdquo;. Open questions &ldquo;What type of car do you want&rdquo; might give a lot of information that would be diffiucult to analyze. Closed questions are a good option if the choices presented are intelligent.</p>

<p>And you can Interview people, observe them in process, ask them to tabulate their experiences while doing something, do focus groups etc.</p>

<h3>User Profiles</h3>

<p>This was a very nice snippet. Similar to copywriting &ndash; a copy for sales is not equal to copy for UX; a good persona for sales may not be a good one for UX.</p>

<p>The major point here is that once you develop a persona &ndash; you should be able to take a look and get something actionable out of it. How does the persona affect your UX design &ndash; if you are not getting any specific &ldquo;Do this not that&rdquo; out, then the user profile is a bad one.</p>

<p>I have seen people advocate building one ideal user profile and customizing the whole experience for that one person. There are also those who want to build several profiles and offer something to each one &ndash; so take your pick!</p>

<h3>Device consideration</h3>

<p>Obviously, the day of building only for laptops is past. Keep in mind the different devices from which content will be consumed. At a minimal level &ndash; keep the design responsive.</p>

<p>Honestly, this section is too big &amp; too rapidly changing to have been adequately covered in a page.</p>

<h3>Design Patterns</h3>

<p>Use design patterns that have proven to be good. Do not reinvent the wheel but also do not confuse a common design pattern to always be a good design pattern.</p>

<p>Really liked the mention of Facebook Hamburger button (didn&rsquo;t know that is what it was called) but yes, am seeing many website employing the same without any need to do so.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 2: UX Crash Course]]></title>
    <link href="http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/ux-crash-course/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-07T09:21:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/ux-crash-course</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>A crash course on UX</h3>

<p><em>I am always bookmarking interesting tutorials that I would do one fine day. Since that day never comes, I have aimed to do one tutorial each day. The topics would broadly be programming, design, marketing and productivity tips. All credit to the original tutorials &ndash; I am just thinking aloud as I type my notes &amp; views on what I read.</em></p>

<p>Day 2: The UX Crash Course <a href="http://thehipperelement.com/post/75476711614/ux-crash-course-31-fundamentals">http://thehipperelement.com/post/75476711614/ux-crash-course-31-fundamentals</a></p>

<h3>What is UX</h3>

<p>A process to make users more effective in whatever their indivdiual goals are.</p>

<h3>Goals</h3>

<p>The core concept here is two pronged: First, find the user &amp; business goals and second, align those goals. It is fascinating that this crash course starts with this point, because I have been part of teams where websites/applications were developed in an environment of zero possibility of this happening. Designers/developers had minimum access to top management to understand the goals (well apart from knowing what the business does) and had no interaction with end users.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, in most practical cases there are plenty of restrictions (time, money, resources) that relegate UX to UI and UI to only following the current best practises.</p>

<p>Either way &ndash; there is no denying that designing experiences without understanding stakeholders is not the best way.</p>

<h3>Ingredients of UX</h3>

<p>Okay so this section is very nicely done &ndash; lots of questions that you should bookmark <a href="http://thehipperelement.com/post/72080847673/daily-ux-crash-course-3-of-31">http://thehipperelement.com/post/72080847673/daily-ux-crash-course-3-of-31</a> . Irrespective of whether you have a full team working or running a single person shop, I guess asking these questions at various stages of progress can only make things better.</p>

<p>The 5 ingredients listed are Pyschology (get into the mind of users, their goals &amp; motivations), Usability (visualize the actions of users, how they use your design), Design (estimate the impressions your design makes on users), Copywriting (Are you using generic text or everything is optimized) and Analysis (Measure, measure, measure)</p>

<p>Couple of points here &ndash; a good UX designer would be exceptionally good in getting into the mind of users. Obviously, there is only a degree to which this is possible. But, if you can track what made the user come to your site, what did he want and how did he go about searching for it &ndash; your designs would start aligning the goals.</p>

<p>The other interesting point is something that is quite new to me &ndash; the copywriting used by the UX designer. I suspect a vast majority of time is spent on visual design and text is treated as commoditized work.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 1: Creating an Octopress Blog on Github]]></title>
    <link href="http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/06/creating-a-github-blog-using-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-06T12:15:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://dpac56.github.io/blog/2014/02/06/creating-a-github-blog-using-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Building an Octopress Blog on Github</h3>

<p><em>I am always bookmarking interesting tutorials that I would do one fine day. Since that day never comes, I have aimed to do one tutorial each day. The topics would broadly be programming, design, marketing and productivity tips. All credit to the original tutorials &ndash; I am just thinking aloud as I type my notes.</em></p>

<p>Day 1: Getting started with Octopress <a href="http://www.tomordonez.com/blog/2012/06/04/creating-a-github-blog-using-octopress/">http://www.tomordonez.com/blog/2012/06/04/creating-a-github-blog-using-octopress/</a></p>

<p>Octopress is a static blogging framework that calls itself “A blogging framework for hackers”. The tutorial at tutsplus (<a href="http://dev.tutsplus.com/tutorials/getting-started-with-octopress--webdesign-11442">http://dev.tutsplus.com/tutorials/getting-started-with-octopress&#8211;webdesign-11442</a>) does a good job of explaining what is the difference between such a static framework and something like Wordpress that needs to ‘do’ something on the server before becoming viewable.</p>

<p>Octopress in itself is pretty famous and used by a lot of programmers. I was a bit wary that the Octopress site hasn’t been updated for a few years and toyed with the idea of trying out Pelican &ndash; that does almost the same thing but is Python based. Maybe, will do that later.</p>

<p>You would need Ruby version 1.9.3 or above for this to work. And since my machine didn’t have that I had to use the Ruby Version Manager (rvm).</p>

<p>As soon as I put in the first command of the tutorial, out popped a message that rvm on Ubuntu is unusable. Good thing though that the link given pointed to a Stackoverflow answer that worked perfectly.</p>

<p>You had to remove the rvm completely and reinstall as per these instructions.</p>

<p>Follow the instructions, and finally when it all ends run the command ruby &mdash;version. It should output to the latest one. I now have 2.1.0</p>

<p>With Ruby you also need RubyGems &ndash; a package management framework for Ruby. Broadly, the programs/libraries/codes in Ruby are in a self contained format called a gem. With RubyGems you can install any of these open source packages directly from the command line.</p>

<p>The commands to install Octopress are pretty simple.</p>

<p>Go to a convenient folder and clone the main repo</p>

<pre><code>git clone git://github.com/imathis/octopress.git octopress
cd octopress
rake install
</code></pre>

<p>At this stage, you are actually ready to see your blog locally with the following</p>

<pre><code>rake preview
</code></pre>

<p>Go to localhost:4000 in your browser &amp; you should see the default theme</p>

<p><em>The deploying to github part is also straightforward but gave me a lot of headache.</em></p>

<p>This is what you need to do. Create a new github repository with name as username.github.com</p>

<p>Run</p>

<pre><code>rake setup_github_pages
</code></pre>

<p>You will need to enter the repository URL in the terminal when prompted. The suggested format is</p>

<pre><code>git@github.com:username/username.github.com.git
</code></pre>

<p>However, entering this format (&amp; after completing the process) I could not deploy on github and kept getting an invalid repository/check access rights error. Finally, I tried entering in this format</p>

<pre><code>git@github.com:username/username.github.com
</code></pre>

<p>And everything worked &ndash; so if you are having some troubles, try checking with the second option as well.</p>

<p>Pushing to github:</p>

<pre><code>rake generate
git add .
git commit -am "Message"
git push origin source
rake deploy
</code></pre>

<p>That should be it and your blog should be viewable on username.github.com (or .io) in some minutes.</p>

<p>Everytime you create a new post</p>

<pre><code>rake new_post ["My first post"]
</code></pre>

<p>they will be stored in the octopress/source/_posts folder and after each modification you can run the above set of git commands to see the changes.</p>

<p>A couple of points:</p>

<ol>
<li>If you are still having trouble, check that the default branch of your github repo is &lsquo;master&rsquo; and not &lsquo;source&rsquo;</li>
<li>The posts in Octopress are in Markdown format &ndash; it is pretty easy to learn &amp; is bare bones. This is where you can take a look <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax#list">http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax#list</a></li>
</ol>


<p>These links might also help in your specific problems:</p>

<p><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/12060903/github-error-repository-not-found-when-installing-octopress">http://stackoverflow.com/questions/12060903/github-error-repository-not-found-when-installing-octopress</a></p>

<p><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/11240797/git-commit-error-repository-invalid">http://stackoverflow.com/questions/11240797/git-commit-error-repository-invalid</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
